<list>

page:

<les><ref>A0001</ref>
<uig>a</uig>
<cyr>аа</cyr>
<lat>A</lat>
1. / [a - a] interj. A! Oh! Well!
<ex>--, jam[b]ar saixan bui! Ah, how beautiful it is</ex>
<ex>--, køgerykei! Oh, what a pityl</ex>
<ex>--, tege ! Yes, do that ></ex>
<ex>--, teimy yy? Oh, is that so?</ex>
<p>1</p>
</les>

<les><ref>A0001</ref>
<uig>a</uig>
<cyr>аа, ээ, оо, өө</cyr>
<lat>A, E</lat>
2 interj. Exclamation used in direct address following the person addressed: O!
<ex>jeke xaγan a! 0 Great Emperor </ex>
<ex>keyked e ! Children !</ex>
<ex>nøkyd e ! Friends! Comrades!</ex>
<p>1</p>
</les>

<les><ref>A0001</ref>
<uig>a</uig>
<cyr></cyr>
<lat>-A, -E</lat>
 SuffiX of the dative locative case and adverbs.
<ex>cerig yn alban-a tataxu. To draft for military service.</ex>
<ex>daruixan-a. :Immediately, forthwith.</ex>
<ex>ene zabar-a. In the meantime, at this juncture.</ex>
<ex>γazar-a. In the place; to the place.</ex>
<p>1</p>
</les>

<les><ref>A0735</ref>
<uig>aqu</uig>
<cyr></cyr>
<lat>A-</lat>
 v . i., aux., and copul. To be (not all forms of this verb are used; see examples also under abacu, abasu, atal-a, axui, azu, azuγu ).
<ex>--zi. Past tense used instead of azuγu (q. v. ).</ex>
<ex>bi ene γazar - -suγai Let me stay at this place.</ex>
<ex>bui --muit. There is.</ex>
<ex>kylijen --γsaγar edyr udaba. [I] have been waiting for many days.</ex>
<ex>sain saγatazu --mui uu? How are you? lit,: are you living well ?)</ex>
<ex>tegyn y - -γsan γazar. The place where he had been.</ex>
<ex>tein --xul-a. If it is or were so.</ex>
<ex>tende - -tuγai. [Let him] be there !</ex>
<ex>tere oruzu irekyi dy bi saγuzu --bai. When he came in I was sitting.</ex>
<p>1</p>
</les>

<les><ref>A1295</ref>
<uig>ab</uig>
<cyr>ав</cyr>
<lat>AB</lat>
1 Intensifying particle before certain adjectives and 'adverbs with initial a.
<ex>-- adali. Absolutely similar or identical</ex>
<ex>-- ariγun. Completely clean or pure; very holy, immaculate</ex>
<p>1</p>
</les>

<les><ref>A1295</ref>
<uig>ab</uig>
<cyr>ав</cyr>
<lat>AB</lat>
2 n. Witchcraft, sorcery, charms; temptation,.allurement, enticement.
<ex>-- tur oruxu. To be allured, yield to temptation.</ex>
<p>1</p>
</les>

<les><ref>A1296</ref>
<uig>aba</uig>
<cyr></cyr>
<lat>ABA</lat>
1 see abu
<p>1</p>
</les>

<les><ref>A1296</ref>
<uig>aba</uig>
<cyr>ав</cyr>
<lat>ABA</lat>
2 n. Chase, hunt, battue.
<ex>-- gøryge, Hunting.</ex>
<ex>-- kiky. To go hunting.</ex>
<ex>-- talbixu. To begin a hunt; to encircle the game on a battue.</ex>
<ex>-- taraxu. The hunters spread out for the battue</ex>
<ex>-- xurljaxu. To call a finish to a hunt.</ex>
<ex>-- zarlaxu. To invite or call for a hunt.</ex>
<ex> ang -- Hunting, trapping.</ex>
<p>1</p>
</les>

<les><ref>A1565</ref>
<uig>abqu</uig>
<cyr>авах</cyr>
<lat>AB-</lat>
 v, t. a) To take, grasp, get hold of. b) To receive, obtain, gain, procure, acquire; to collect (as taxes); to buy; . to absorb, draw in; to adopt; to conceive. c) To remove, take off. d) As an auxiliary verb -preceded by imperfect or modal converbs describes the action as performance in the interest, on behalf, at the wish, or in the direction of the subject. e) As an auxiliary verb preceded by the perfect converb describes the action as momentary. f) The modal and perfect converbs of this verb preceded by the ablative case have the meaning of "beginning with, from. Since”
<ex>--cu ireky. To bring.</ex>
<ex>--cu jabuxu. To take and go, take away; to take care of.</ex>
<ex>--cu odxu. To take away, carry off.</ex>
<ex>--uγad ire! Take and corne! Bring!</ex>
<ex>γar taγan --xu. To take in one’s hand[s].</ex>
<ex>xojar γar ijer --xu. To take or receive with both hands (out of politeness).</ex>
<ex>zisij -e - -xu, To take as an example,</ex>
<ex>ama --xu. To promise, pledge.</ex>
<ex>ami --xu. To save life; to take a rest.</ex>
<ex>amisx-a --xu. To breathe; to take a breath; to take a short rest.</ex>
<ex>amta --xu. To acquire a taste for.</ex>
<ex>arγ -a kemzij -e - -xu. To take measures or steps,</ex>
<ex>azil du --xu. To hire tor work.</ex>
<ex>cigig •..-xu.To absorb moisture.</ex>
<ex>cimege --xu..' To obtain informacion.</ex>
<ex>egyn ece - -cu yzebesy. Looking from this viewpoint.</ex>
<ex>ekener . --xu. To take a wife, marry.</ex>
<ex>ezelen --xu. To take possession of; to occupy.</ex>
<ex>gergei --xu To take a wife, marry.</ex>
<ex>kegelt --xu. To become pregnant (of animals).</ex>
<ex>kycyn --xu. To gain strength; to grow fat ( of animals).</ex>
<ex>kylijen --xu. To accept, receive.</ex>
<ex>øs --xu. To avenge, take revenge.</ex>
<ex>salki --xu. To catch a cold.</ex>
<ex>sanaγ-a -~xu. To conceive an idea, grasp the meaning.</ex>
<ex>sanal --xu. To get someone's opinion, gather opinions.</ex>
<ex>sezig --xu. To become .suspicious.</ex>
<ex>tarγu --xu. To gain weight, grow fat (of animals).</ex>
<ex>terigyn i --xu. To take first place.</ex>
<ex>usu - -xu. To get water; to absorb water; to be flooded.</ex>
<ex>xurijan --xu. _ To receive; to collect; to confiscate.</ex>
<ex>yge --xu. To be receptive to somebody's request; to take or follow advice.</ex>
<ex>yge ji --xu. To interrogate, question, give a hearing ; to receive testimony or statement.</ex>
<ex>ynyr - -xu. To smell or get the odor or scent of</ex>
<ex>yrecilezy - -xu. To adopt a child.</ex>
<ex>yzygyr - -xu. To occupy first place, stand at the head of.</ex>
<ex>ziruy --xu. To take a photograph, have one's picture taken.</ex>
<ex> ami --xu. To take one's life, kill. See also b.</ex>
<ex>emegel --xu. To take off a saddle.</ex>
<ex>malaγ-a ben --xu. To take off one's hat or cap.</ex>
<ex>toluγai --xu. To decapitate.</ex>
<ex>urγuca --xu. To reap, harvest.</ex>
<ex>bicizy --xu. To write down or note.</ex>
<ex>surcu --xu. To learn, -study.</ex>
<ex>tatan --xu. To attract to oneself; to win. (as supporters, etc.); to recruit.</ex>
<ex>xarazu - -xu. To take notice.</ex>
<ex>xudaldun --xu. To buy.</ex>
<ex>bariγad - - !Grab him I Grab it !</ex>
<ex>cokiγad - -xu. To strike a blow.</ex>
<ex>ekin ece –un from the beginning</ex>
<ex>ørlyge ece --uγad. Since morning.</ex>
<ex>tende ece --uγad ende kyrtel-e. From there to here.</ex>
<p>1</p>
</les>

<les><ref>A1565</ref>
<uig>abugad</uig>
<cyr></cyr>
<lat>ABUГAD</lat>
 Perfect converb of ab-, See ab-, a and f.
<p>1</p>
</les>



</list>
